Mss.B.B122 Mss.B.B122
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Bache papers, 1779-1793
Mss.B.B122
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Letters of a dutiful child to his parents Richard Bache and Sarah Franklin Bache, and to his grandfather, Benjamin Franklin; also letters to William Jones, Robert Frazer, and Margaret H. Markoe, his fiancée. Also photostats of letters to Robert Alexander of Virginia, from the originals in University of Virginia Library.
50 items, some of which are photostat copies from originals in the Yale University and University of Virginia libraries.
Alexander, Robert
Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
Frazer, R., (Robert)
Jones, William, 1760-1831
Markoe, Margaret Hartman
Box 1
Existence and Location of Originals note
Location of the original is unknown.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Accessioned, 1954.
Biographical/Historical note
Benjamin Franklin Bache, the grandson of Benjamin Franklin, worked as a printer and journalist.
General note
Entries for 1784 were printed by Bernard Faÿ, "Paris, à la fin de l'ancien régime, vu par un petit garcon de Philadelphie," Franco-American Review 1(1936-37):317.
Early American History Note
The Benjamin Franklin Bache Collection is composed primarily of correspondence sent from B.F. Bache. The vast majority dates to his time in Europe during the American Revolution while a young child under the care of his grandfather, Benjamin Franklin, who was then serving as one of America’s ambassadors to France. These letters consist of B.F. Bache writing from his school in Switzerland to his grandfather in Paris (often in French) and to his parents in America (in English). Most of the letters relay information on B.F.’s formal education and his experience learning the printing trade. The only letter dated after Bache’s time in Europe is a personal letter mourning the loss of Benjamin Franklin that he wrote to his soon-to-be-wife, Margaret Markoe. The letter contains one of the most detailed accounts of Franklin’s last days.
American Revolution; Americans Abroad; Diplomatic History; Education; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Printing and Publishing; Switzerland -- Description and travel.
- Series One: General Correspondence, 1779-1793; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, May 30, 1779; 7" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Scope and Contents note
    A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.1)
  - Letter to his grandfather [Benjamin Franklin], Oct. 25, 1779; 6 3/4" x 8 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 3p. and end. Partly in French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.2)
  - Letter to his Papa [i.e. Benjamin Franklin], Dec. 21, 1779; 6 1/2" x 8 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.3)
  - Letter to his Papa, [Benjamin] Franklin, March 25, 1780; 7" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.4)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, May 6, 1780; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Seal. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.5)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, May 30, 1780; 7" x 9 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Seal. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.6)
  - Letter to [Benjamin Franklin;], June 19, 1780; Marignac, Gabriel Louis Gallisard de
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. On same sheet with letter from B.F.Bache to Dr. Franklin of same date. (see B.F.Bache. Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.7) ----Copy of both letters, under date of June 5, 1780.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, July 18, 1780; 7" x 9 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Seal In French. (see his Letter to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.8)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Sept., 1780; 7" x 9 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Seal In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.9) End: Recd. Sept. 20, 1780.
  - Letter to grandfather [B. Franklin], Oct. 17, 1780; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.10) Addressed in another hand: Richd. Bache...
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Nov. 26, 1780; 7" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Seal. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.11)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, March 26, 1781; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Seal. In French. (see his Letters to B.Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.12)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, May 26, 1781; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.13)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, June 30, 1781; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.14)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Sept. 12, [1781?]; 6 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. Faded. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.15)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Feb. 21, 1782; 7 1/2" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.16)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, July 27, 1782; 6 3/4" x 8 3/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.17)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Aug. 30, 1782; 6 3/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, 18)
  - Letter to his Papa [Richard Bache], Sept. 15, 1782; 6 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 2p., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.19)
  - Letter to his Mama [Sarah Bache], Sept. 15, 1782; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Geneva, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.20)
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin [Geneva,]., Sept., 1782; 6 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.21)
  - Letter to his Papa and Mama [Richard and Sarah Bache, 1782; 7" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin ,1769-1798
    ca.]. A.L.S. 2p. and end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.22) Loss of the English army under Lord Cornwallis. Writes often to his grandfather, B. Franklin.
  - Letter to Richard Bache, July 27, 1783; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.23) Mentions his grandpapa, B. Franklin.
  - Letter to his Mother [Sarah] Bache, July 27, 1783; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin,1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.24)
  - Letter to his papa and Mama [Richard and Sarah Bache], Sept. 13, 1783; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 2p., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.25) Is now living at Passy with his grandpapa and cousin.
  - Letter to his Papa and Mamma [Richard and Sarah Bache], Oct. 30, 1783; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, Photostat of c. of L. 1p. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.31) Is with his grandfather at Passy. Air balloons. Experiments made by his cousin [W.T. Franklin]. From copy in Yale university lib.
  - Letter to Richard Bache, Dec. 27, 1783; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.27) Is learning to print. His grandfather longs to go to America.
  - Letter to his Mamma [Sarah Bache], Dec. 27, 1783; 7 1/4" x 9 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 2p. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.26) Is learning to print. Went to Paris to see the illuminations made for the peace. Air balloons.
  - Letter to "Mon cher ami", Jan. 19, 1784; 8" x 9 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, Letterpress c. of A.L.S. 1p. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no. 28) Mentions his grandfather, B. Franklin.
  - Letter to Rich[ard] Bache, Nov. 11, 1784; 7 1/2" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no. 29) Is learning to cast types; hopes his grandfather will be able to go to America the following summer.
  - Letter to his Mamma [Sarah Bache], Feb. 9, 1785; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see his Letters to B. Franklin and R. and S. Bache, no.30) Addressed to Rich. Bache. Mentions his grandfather, B. Franklin; still learning to cast types.
  - Letter to [Margaret H. Markoe], May 2, 10, 1790; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Philadelphia, A.L. 4p. (see B.F.Bache Papers.) Death of Franklin and distribution of his estate according to the will.
    Originally cataloged as: B B122.4
  - Receipted bill to Robert Frazer, June 8, 1793; 5 3/4" x 8 1/4"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    A.D.S. 1p. and end. Payment for printing, Sept. 16,1792-Feb. 15,1793.
  - Will, Sept. 7, 1798; B B122.w; 13 3/4" x 8"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin,1769-1798.
    D.S. 2p. and end. Witnessed, Nov. 13,1798, and S: James Robinson, Wm. Duane. Deposited by the Register of Wills Office, Phila.; Dec.10,1954 - restricted., cf. terms of use, Legal folder.
    General note
    Not found 5/2011
  - Letter to W[illia]m Jones, 2nd St., Undated; 5 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    n.d. A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Regarding delivery of newspaper.
    Originally cataloged as B B122.1
- Series Two: Letters to Robert Alexander, June 20 1785 -Oct. 21, 1787; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
  Photostats of A.L.S. 6 items. In French and English. (originals in the Samuel M. Wilson Library, University of Kentucky.) Letters dated: June 20, July 2, July 16, Oct. 30, 1785; Oct. 16, 1786. and Oct. 21, 1787. Refers to B. Franklin.
  Originally cataloged as B122.3 no.1-6